plant-based diets are gaining popularity
among athletes in this video find out
why folks are drawn to plant-based diets
for athletic performance and recovery
[Music]
consumer interest in eating plant-based
has surged over the last few years and
athletes are no exception well in the
past meat was seen as an irreplaceable
performance-enhancing food today the
trend is developing the opposite
direction thanks in part to
documentaries like the game changers for
which i was honored to play a role as
scientific advisor
several high-profile athletes from
heavyweight champion boxers to tennis
players have tried fueling with plants
athletes have increasingly been adopting
plant-based diets not only for the
related health benefits but for
perceived improvements in endurance
performance in fact even by 2016 there
are reports of up to a third of ultra
endurance runners for example shunning
meat
increasing plant-based foods may boost
vasodilatory meaning artery dilating
antioxidant and anti-inflammatory
properties of the diet which can lead to
improved blood flow reduced oxidative
stress and inflammation and thus
theoretically enhance endurance
performance reduce muscle damage and
speed recovery exercise itself can
release free radicals that can also lead
to muscle fatigue reduced athletic
performance and impaired recovery but
the antioxidants concentrated in plant
foods can help extinguish them
here's the level of oxidative stress
before and after
running for a few hours a doubling of
this oxidative stress marker but that's
without blueberries eat a cup and a half
of blueberries an hour before the run
you can significantly blunt the stress
no wonder that eating even a cup of
blueberries may improve exercise
performance whereas eating meat
could actually make things worse
same with inflammation shifting to a
dietary pattern with more plants and
less animal source food has been shown
to attenuate inflammation
a systematic review of meta-analysis
comparing common biomarkers of
inflammation found that meat-free diets
appear to be favorable in all cases and
not just inflammation but immune status
having a strong immune system is
important for athletes especially
endurance athletes as they are often
immunocompromised which increases risk
of upper respiratory tract infection
after a marathon there can be about a
six-fold higher odds of coming down with
an infection and after an ultra marathon
as many as 68 fall ill within the
ensuing two weeks but a a better immune
system could translate into less illness
which means more time training for the
plant-based athlete though this is yet
to be studied directly
we also know there's an ergogenic
meaning performance enhancing effect to
nitrates and nitrates in the bloodstream
of vegetarians about 20 percent higher
and vegans 40 percent higher likely do
to their eating more nitrate-rich
vegetables such as beets spinach and
other greens
and then there are all the health
benefits that could boost performance in
the long term it is well documented that
plant-based diets reduce the risk of
chronic disease such as cardiovascular
disease diabetes metabolic syndrome and
cancer and all-cause mortality
meaning living a significantly longer
life
but do high-performing athletes really
need cardiovascular protection
surprisingly and that's why i did this
video endurance athletes may have more
advanced atherosclerosis more heart
muscle damage compared to sedentary
individuals male athletes had a higher
percentage of atherosclerotic plaques in
their coronary arteries compared with
sedentary males a higher prevalence of
high coronary artery calcium a greater
number of atherosclerotic plaques
including multi-vessel plaques and
greater proportions squeezing off blood
flow more than 50 percent
marathon runners
found to have increased total
atherosclerotic plaque volume calcified
plaques non-calcified plaques
paradoxically worse
atherosclerosis in their coronary
arteries which may then translate into
more damage to the heart muscle itself
three times more than match sedentary
individuals they are running
the risk of coronary events it's the
kind of heart damage you see after heart
attacks
but wait
why
why do studies show that well-trained
athletes are at significant risk for
atherosclerosis and heart damage it may
not be because they're over stressing
their heart with movement but rather
over stressing their heart with
saturated fat and cholesterol endurance
athletes can eat five six seven thousand
calories a day so if you're eating twice
the big macs no wonder their poor hearts
are getting hammered
that's where plant-based diets come in
the only diet shown to be able to
reverse the progression of heart disease
in the majority of patients
yes such diets may also contribute to
improved performance and accelerated
recovery but most importantly will allow
you to recover and maintain your
long-term health athletic performance
suffers when you're dead
[Music]
you